Guide to the M. M. Schiffer Papers
Stanford University Libraries.
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives.
M. M. Schiffer Papers
1953-1979
SC0654
Schiffer, M. M.
4 Linear feet
Book chapter, articles, lectures, and some correspondence dating from Schiffer's tenure at Stanford University.
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives. Stanford University Libraries. 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: speccollref@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Transfer from Mathematics Library, 2002
Information about Access
There are no restrictions on access.
Biography
M. M. Schiffer was considered an authority on complex variables and conformal mapping; his special province was the application of these fields to mathematical physics, particularly to hydrodynamics. A native of Berlin, Schiffer earned his undergraduate degree at Friedrich-Wilhelm University in 1930 and pursued his graduate work at the Hebrew University in Jerusalem, earning his Ph.D. in 1938. He taught there until 1946, when he moved to the United States and subsequently taught at Harvard and Princeton. He joined the Stanford faculty in 1952, serving as executive head of the Mathematics Department from 1954 to 1959. In 1967 Schiffer was appointed to the Robert Grimmett Professorship of Mathematics, a position he held until his retirement in 1977. While at Stanford he was involved in the School Mathematics Study Group and co-authored many technical reports for the Applied Mathematics and Statistics Laboratory. He died in 1997.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
These papers date from his tenure at Stanford University and consist largely of manuscripts and typescripts of book chapters, articles, and lectures. Topics include conformal mapping, relativity, differential equations, functions of complex variables, and mathematical physics. Other items include research notes and letters from Robert W. Fuller, Nicolai Minorsky, and J. G. Van der Corput.
Access Terms
Corput, J. G. van der (Johannes Gualtherus), b. 1890.; Fuller, Robert W.; Minorsky, Nicolai, 1885-; Conformal mapping.; Functions of complex variables.; General relativity (Physics)--Mathematics.; Mathematics--Scientific applications.; Mathematics.
Collection Contents
- Book Chapters
  - Chapter 3 Tensor analysis (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chapter 4 Tensors in physics (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chapter 5 The gravitational field equations in free space (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chapter 6 The Schwarzschild solution and its consequences: experimental tests of general relativity (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chapter 10 [no title] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chapter 11 Cosmology and astronomy (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chapter [11] Cosmology and astronomy (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chapter 12 Cosmological models (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chapter [12] Cosmological models (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chapter 13 Electromagnetism and general relativity (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bibliographies for the chapters (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Table of contents; part of chapter 13 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Assorted additions to chapters (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chapter 1 Phase plane; singular points, (1956) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Chapter 2 Conservative systems (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Chapter 3 Limit cycles of Poincare (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Chapter 4 Geometric analysis of periodic solutions (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Chapter 5 Stability (variational equations; characteristic exponents) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Chapter 6 Stability (Liapounov) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Chapter 7 Theory of bifurcations (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Chapter 8 Cylindrical and toroidal phase spaces (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chapter 9 Methods of solutions by series (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Chapter 10 Periodic solutions (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chapter 11 Determination of characteristic exponents (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Chapter 12 Asymptotic methods (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Chapter 13 Asymptotic methods of Kryloff - Bogolinboff (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Chapter 14 Stroboscopic method (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Other Writings
  - Applications of variational methods in the theory of conformal mapping - tss and correspondence, 1955-56 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Applications of variational methods in the theory of conformal mapping - mss (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Calculus - mss, not in Schiffer's hand (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Complex analysis I. Stanford - mss, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Conformal mapping. Stanford (1 of 3) - mss, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Conformal mapping. Stanford (2 of 3) - mss, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Conformal mapping. Stanford (3 of 3) - mss, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Differentiable and sense preserving mappings - mss (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Differential and integral calculus. Stanford - mss, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - External problems on doubly connected domains - mss (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Fredholm Eigen Values of Plane Domains, Pacific Journal of Mathematics, Vol. 7, No. 2, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Fredholm Eigenvalues and conformal mapping of multiply connected domains (Schiffer and G. Springer) - tss (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Function of a complex variable I. Stanford - mss, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Function of a complex variable. Stanford (1 of 2) - mss, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Function of a complex variable. Stanford (2 of 2) - mss, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Galois theory. Stanford Spring Quarter [possibly a lecture] - mss, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Introduction to general relativity. Stanford (1 of 2) - mss, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Introduction to general relativity. Stanford (2 of 2) - mss, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Mathematical methods of physics. Stanford - mss, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts: period matrix; section 2 distortion theorems - mss (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - On the fourth coefficient of bounded univalent functions (Schiffer and O. Tammi) - mss, not in Schiffer's hand (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Ordinary differential equations. Stanford - mss, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Partial Differential Equations of the elliptic type - tss (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Partial Differential Equations of the elliptic type - tss (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Perspectives in mathematics. Stanford - mss, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - QC mappings, chapters on - tss (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Some consequences of the Riemann-Roch theorem - mss (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Theory of analytic functions. Stanford - mss, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Theory of the second (?) variation - mss (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Variation of domain functionals. Pasadena, - mss, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Research Notes
  - Miscellaneous: formulas (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Notes: A non-local estimate for A5 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Notes and reprint, The Local Maximum Theorem for the Coefficients of Univalent Functions (P. R. Garabedian and Schiffer), Archive for Rational Mechanics and Analysis, Vol. 26, No. 1, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Notes and reprints, Pederson, Roger N. On Unitary Properties of Grunsky's Matrix, Archive for Rational Mechanics and Analysis, Vol. 29, No. 5, 1968; On the Bieberbach Conjecture for Even n (Garabedian, Ross & Schiffer), Journal of Mathematics and Mechanics, Nov. 14, No. 6, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Notes 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Notes 2 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Notes 3 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Notes 4 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Correspondence and Miscellaneous
  - Fuller, Robert W. - letter, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Minorsky, Nicolai - correspondence and text, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Minorsky, Nicolai - correspondence, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Van der Corput, J. G. - letter, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Schiffer, Dinah - "You" [personal information on Schiffer as a child] (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Additional Materials: Book Chapters, Accession ARCH.2015-049
  - Physical Model for Conformal Mapping I (Handwritten) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Physical Model for Conformal Mappings I (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Physical Model for Conformal Mappings I (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Potential Theory in the Plane II (Handwritten) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Potential Theory in the Plane II (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Transfinite Diameter and Lemniscates III (Handwritten) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Transfinite Diameter and Lemniscates III (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Normal Families; Riemann's Mapping Theorem IV (Handwritten) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Normal Families; Riemann's Mapping Theorem IV (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Normal Families; Riemann's Mapping Theorem IV (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Techniques and Applications of Conformal Mapping V (Handwritten) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Techniques and Applications of Conformal Mapping V (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Conformal Mapping at the Boundary VI (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Conformal Mapping at the Boundary VI (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Elementary Theory of Univalent Functions VII (Handwritten) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Elementary Theory of Univalent Functions VII (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Kernel Functions and Their Properties VIII (Handwritten) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Kernel Function and Their Properties VIII (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Applications of the Kernel Functions to Conformal Mapping IX (Handwritten) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Applications of the Kernel Functions to Conformal Mapping IX (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Variational Methods in Conformal Mapping X (Handwritten) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Extremum Problems in Conformal Mappings XI (Handwritten) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - The Lowner Differential Equation XIV (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Variations within Special Families of Univalent Functions XV (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Plates (Box 1, Folder 25)